Guide to the Eric Hampton Dance records, 1981-2012 MS2339
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Eric Hampton Dance records
1981-2012
1991-2002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Kraft, Ned
Moncure Williams, Harriet
Hampton, Eric
MS2339
3.5 Linear Feet 7 document boxes
This collection contains correspondence, notes, financial documents, licensing agreements, programs, flyers, DVDs, photographs, printed media reviews, and other records related to the operation of Eric Hampton Dance. The material, which dates from 1981 to 2012. The Washington area dance company was founded in 1991 by choreographer and ballet instructor Eric Hampton.
Biographical / Historical
Eric Hampton Dance (EHD) was founded in 1991 by Eric Hampton, revered ballet instructor and talented choreographer. The purpose of the company was to bring Hampton's unique vision of classically inspired contemporary movement to audiences throughout the Washington, D.C. area. EHD attracted distinguished dancers and earned both local and national praise. The company received funding from various arts foundations, including the DC Commission on the Arts and Humanities, the National Endowment for the Arts, the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, the Maryland Youth Ballet, the Morris and Gwendolyn Cafritz Foundation, and the Eugene and Agnes E. Meyer Foundation. Eric Hampton Dance also had annual benefits to raise money and support for the Whitman-Walker Clinic, a non-profit health center specializing in HIV/AIDS and LGBT health care for the D.C. area.
Eric Hampton (1947-2001) was a distinguished choreographer and dance instructor in the Washington, D.C. area. Hampton graduated from Interlochen Arts Academy and the Juilliard School of Dance. In 1969, he moved to Europe and joined the Netherlands Dance Theater and the Scapino Ballet. In 1978, Hampton returned to the U.S. where he joined the Washington Ballet as a soloist and resident choreographer. During this time, he also directed his own dance studio, Dance Downtown, until 1986. In 1981, Hampton became a faculty member and resident choreographer for the Maryland Youth Ballet. In 1991, Hampton founded his own company, Eric Hampton Dance. Harriet Moncure Fellows (née Williams), one of Hampton's fellow instructors at the Maryland Youth Ballet, became his artistic assistant at EHD. Tragically, Mr. Hampton was diagnosed with Lou Gehrig's disease (ALS) in 1997 and passed away in February 2001 at the age of 54. After his death, Hampton's works were left in the care of his close friend and colleague, Harriet Moncure Fellows. In 2012, Fellows helped establish the Eric Hampton Dance Foundation (EHDF) which licenses Hampton's choreographic work. Fellows holds the positions of President and Treasurer at EHDF. Elisa Clark, who received training from Eric Hampton and the Maryland Youth Ballet, is currently the Director of Repertory for the foundation.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, notes, financial documents, licensing agreements, programs, flyers, DVDs, photographs, and printed media reviews. The material dates from 1981 to 2012. These are records related to the operation of Eric Hampton Dance. Eric Hampton Dance was founded in 1991 by choreographer and ballet instructor Eric Hampton.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Management, marketing, and fundraising files, Performance files, and Reviews and publicity files
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ned Kraft, 4/20/2015 (2015.028)
Dance companies; Dancers; Dance; Kraft, Ned
- Management, marketing and fundraising files, 1988-2005; 1991-2001; MS2339 Series 1; Moncure Williams, Harriet; Kraft, Ned; Hampton, Eric; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series include marketing packets, grant applications, tax information, donor correspondence, Board of Directors communication, newsletters, photographs, resumes, position descriptions, fundraising, budgets, and event planning. They range in date from 1988 to 2005, and represent the more formal business and management aspects of Eric Hampton Dance.
  - Eric Hampton - Personal, 1988-2001; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mayor's Art Awards Ceremony, 1991-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thank You Letters to EHD, 1991-1998; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budgets, 1992-1994; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dance/USA, 1992-1994; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - DC City Arts Program Materials, 1992-1994; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sample Tickets, 1992-1994; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Promotional and Grant Materials, 1992-1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fundraising - Corporate, 1992-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fundraising - Donors, 1992-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Planning, 1992-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tax Documents, 1992-1998; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cafritz Application, 1993; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Marketing Package, 1993; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Production Calendars, 1993-1994; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Programs - Advertising and Thank You Letters, 1993-1994; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fundraising - Foundations, 1993-1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Marketing, 1993-1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Director Letters, 1993-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dancers - Board Communication Consent/Release Forms & Policies, 1993-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Grant Materials, 1993-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Contracts & Sample Contracts, 1993-1998; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Food & Future Event, 1993-1998; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising - Government Grants, 1994; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - District of Columbia - Annual Reports, 1994-1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grant Proposal Rejections, 1994-1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Donors - Thank You Letters, 1994-1998; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1994-1998; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - DC City Arts Program Materials, 1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - DC Grants-In-Aid Materials, 1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photocopies of Photographs from EHD at the Kennedy Center, 1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Position Descriptions, 1995; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jim Byers - Consultant, 1995-1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Xerox Images, 1995-1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - DC City Arts Program Materials, 1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - DC Grants-In-Aid Materials, 1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - NEA Choreographer's Fellowship Materials, 1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Marketing Package, 1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Meyer Foundation Meeting, 1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Post Office - Bulk Mail, 1996; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - IRS Nonprofit Status, 1996-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Meyer Foundation Grant Materials, 1996-1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cafritz Application Materials, 1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - DC City Arts Program Materials, 1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - DC Grants-In-Aid Individual Materials, 1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - DC Grants-In-Aid Materials, 1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Grant Applications, 1997; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Maryland Youth Ballet - Benefit and Fundraising Materials, 1998 July - 2000 October; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Topics for August 2000 Newsletter, 2000 August; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Eric Hampton Newsletter, 2001 February; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Eric Hampton/MYB Works Fund Benefit Materials, 2001 February - 2001 October; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Eric Hampton Newsletter, 2002 January; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Eric Hampton CV and Biographical Notes, 2005; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Eric Hampton Dance Packet, undated; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Eric Hampton Resumes, undated; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Guest Book (blank), undated; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photographs and Negatives, undated; MS2339 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Performance files, 1989-2012; 1991-2001; MS2339 Series 2; Kraft, Ned; Hampton, Eric; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
  Organized into 3 subseries: Programs and special event materials, Music rights agreements, and Audiovisual materials.
  The materials in this series include correspondence, licensing agreements, dance programs, flyers, schedules, invoices, and DVD footage of various dance performances. They range in date from 1989 to 2012, and represent the performances and special events planned by Eric Hampton Dance.
  - Music rights agreements, 1991-2001; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1; 0.25 Linear Feet
    The materials in this subseries include music rights correspondence and licensing agreements for Eric Hampton Dance performances. The material dates from 1991 to 2001, and it represents the types of songs and performances done by Eric Hampton Dance at this time.
    - Carl Fischer, Inc. - "Slow Movement", 1991-1994; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Music and Licensing, 1991-1995; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - EMI Music Publishing - "Fon Fon Odeon", 1992-1999; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Theodore Presser Co. - "Chants D'Auvergne", 1994-1995; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Theodore Presser Co. - "La Revue de Cuisine", 1994-2001; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Durand et Cie - "Le Tombeau de Couperin", 1995; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Boosey & Hawkes - "Four Sea Interludes", 1995-1996; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - European American Music - Hindemith, 1995-1999; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Boosey & Hawkes - Stravinsky, 1996; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Theodore Presser Co. - "Meadow", 1996; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "How Do I Love Thee" - Music Licensing, 1996-2001; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Intellectual Property Issues, 1997-1998; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Boosey & Hawkes - Bernstein, 1997; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Programs and special event materials, 1989-2012; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2; 1 Linear Feet
    The materials in this subseries include dance programs, flyers, event schedules, invoices, and other materials related to Eric Hampton Dance performances. The materials range in date from 1989 to 2012.
    - Levine School of Music Events, 1989-1994; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Other Dance Companies, 1990-2006; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Whitman-Walker Benefit Programs, 1991; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - EHD - Programs, 1991-2001; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Whitman-Walker Benefit Performances, 1992; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - William & Mary Performances, 1992; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Lifelink Benefit Performances, 1992-1993; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Dance Place Performances, 1992-1994; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Mary Washington College Performances, 1992-1994; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Key West Gay Arts Festival Performances, 1993; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - WALA - Smithsonian Symposium, 1993; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Whitman-Walker Benefit Performances, 1993; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Arlington Dance Theater Performances, 1993-1995; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Performance Announcements, 1993-2001; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Maryland Youth Ballet - The Nutcracker, 1994; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Whitman-Walker Benefit Performances, 1994; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Usher Invitations for Whitman-Walker Clinic, 1994 June; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Kennedy Center Performances, 1994-1995; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Program Biographies, 1994-1995; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Whitman-Walker Clinic and Eric Hampton Dance Benefit Invitations, 1995 September-1996 September; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Dance Place Performances, 1995-1998; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Kennedy Center Performances, 1996; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Kennedy Center Performances, 1997; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Reston Community Center, 1997; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Eric Hampton Dance - Dance Place, 1997 January - 1997 April; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Eric Hampton Dance: Reston Community Center, 1997 April 9; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence: Eric Hampton Dance at the Kennedy Center, 1997 July-1997 September; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Maryland Council for Dance, 1997-1998; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Mount Vernon College - The InSeries, 1997-1998; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Mount Vernon College Performances, 1997-1998; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Feet First Modern Dance Collective, 1997 October-1998 January; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Eric Hampton Benefits, 1997 November-1999 December; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Maryland Youth Ballet Programs, 1997-2007; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Eric Hampton Dance - Dance Place, 1998; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Maryland Council for Dance: State Dance Festival - Washington College, 1998 August-1998 October; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Juilliard Dance, 1998-1999; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Eric Hampton Dance - Juilliard School of Dance, 1998-2012; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Karen & Alvin Dance Programs, 2000; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Jewish Community Center Performances, 2000 January; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Stagebill for the Washington Ballet at the Warner Theatre, 2000 March; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Eric Hampton Dance - Dance Place, 2000-2001; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Maryland Arts Festival: En l'air - In Flight, 2001 July 21; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Jewish Community Center - Tribute to Eric Hampton, 2001-2002; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - EHD - Last Shows, 2001 October-2002 January; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Metro DC Dance Awards, 2005-2010; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Audiovisual materials, 1995-2001; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 3; 0.25 Linear Feet
    This subseries inlcudes 6 DVDs containing footage of various dance performances involving Eric Hampton or Eric Hampton Dance. The materials range in date from 1995 to 2001.
    - DVD: "Senseless Acts of Beauty" - Eric Hampton Dance, 1995; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - DVD: Maryland Youth Ballet - "Meadow", 1996 September 18; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - DVD: Eric Hampton Dance - "Let Me Count the Ways" Concert, 1996 September 19; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - DVD: Eric Hampton Dance presents "Prayers and Nightmares", 1997 September 13; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - DVD: Eric Hampton Memorial Concert - Maryland Youth Ballet and Friends, 2001 October 20; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - DVD: Selected Excerpts from the Choreography of Eric Hampton, undated; MS2339 Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Reviews and publicity files, 1981-2002; MS2339 Series 3; Kraft, Ned; Hampton, Eric; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  The materials in this series include newspaper clippings and online printouts of Eric Hampton Dance event listings, reviews, articles, and interviews. They range in date from 1981 to 2002, and represent Eric Hampton and his dance company's standing in the local community. This series also contains materials related to Eric Hampton's personal battle with ALS and his death in 2001.
  - EHD Reviews, 1981-2002; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - EHD Publicity, 1991-1994; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - EHD Newspaper Publicity, 1993-2000; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - EHD Reviews, 1993-2001; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Eric Hampton Dance Press, 1995-1998; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - The Washington Post: Review by Sarah Kaufman, 1997 March 10; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Washington Post original press: "Prayers and Nightmares", 1997 September; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Press Reviews, 1997 September-1998 March; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Interview with Eric Hampton for Dance International Magazine, 1997 November-1998 January; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Dance News, Vol. 26, No. 6, 1999 February; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Eric Hampton Dance News, 1999 April; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Thirteen/WNET - On Our Own Terms: Moyers on Dying, 2000 May-2000 September; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Eric Hampton Obituary File, 2001; MS2339 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 13)